A Finding Aid to the Hedda Sterne Papers in the Archives of American Art AAA.sterhedd
Archives of American Art
Hedda Sterne papers
1939-1977
AAA.sterhedd
Archives of American Art
1.3 Linear feet
The papers of painter Hedda Sterne measure 1.3 linear feet and date from 1939 to 1977. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including extensive correspondence from Sterne's second husband, the artist and New Yorker illustrator Saul Steinberg; writings; exhibition files; printed material; drawings and 3 sketchbooks; photographs and slides of Sterne, her family, and her work; and originals of Antoine de Saint-Exupéry's work Lettre A Leon Werth and 4 drawings Saint-Exupéry sent to Sterne.
Sterne, Hedda, 1910-
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Hedda Sterne donated her papers in 1970, 1971, and 1972.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives is an oral history interview with Hedda Sterne conducted by Phyllis Tuchman, December 17, 1981, for the Archives of American Art's Mark Rothko and His Times oral history project. Additional correspondence and photographs of Sterne are located in the Saul Steinberg papers at the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Yale University.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 144-145, and 5028 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing and the microfilm is incomplete.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter Hedda Sterne (1910-2011) lived in New York City and was known for working in many artistic styles, including surrealism and abstract expressionism. She was the only woman in the group of abstract expressionists known as "The Irascibles."
Sterne was born in Bucharest, Romania to Simon Lindenberg, a high school language teacher, and his wife Eugenie. Her early interest in art was encouraged by her family and, after graduating from high school at the age of seventeen, she traveled to Vienna to study art. In 1932, she married childhood friend and businessman Frederick Stern. Through the 1930s, she continued to develop as an artist, traveling between Bucharest and Paris, where she attended Fernand Léger's atelier for a time. In 1939, her work with torn paper collages at that year's Paris Salon caught the eye of Hans Arp, who convinced her to exhibit at Peggy Guggenheim's Paris gallery. The chaos and persecution of Jews during World War II precipitated Sterne's arrival in America, where she joined her husband in New York City.
In New York, Peggy Guggenheim welcomed Sterne into her circle of artist friends and invited her to exhibit in Guggenheim's gallery, Art of This Century. In 1944, Sterne remarried the artist and New Yorker illustrator Saul Steinberg and became a U.S. citizen. Through the 1940s, Sterne created works in realist and surrealist styles, but by the late 1940s, she began exploring abstract expressionism. In 1943, Sterne exhibited at the Wakefield Gallery, where she met the gallery manager Betty Parsons and where she received her first one woman show in 1945. After Betty Parsons opened her own gallery in 1946, Sterne joined Parsons' stable and continued to meet and befriend other prominent abstract artists. In 1950, she signed an open letter along with 14 other artists protesting the Metropolitan Museum's conservatism towards abstract art. This led to a feature article in Life magazine where she was the only woman to be photographed alongside "The Irascibles." This group included Jackson Pollock, Willem de Kooning, Barnett Newman, Mark Rothko, and Ad Reinhardt, among others. Through the 1950s, Sterne continued to explore new avenues of art by painting cityscapes, abstract mechanical structures, portraits, and faces, and by using mediums ranging from oil, spray paint, pen and ink, pencil, and diary/text reproductions on stretched canvas.
In 1960, Sterne and Steinberg divorced but remained friends until his death in 1999. The recipient of numerous awards and one woman shows, retrospectives of her work were exhibited at the Montclair Art Museum (1977), Queens Museum of Art (1985), and the Krannert Art Museum (2006). Sterne died in her home in Manhattan in 2011 at the age of 100.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter Hedda Sterne measure 1.3 linear feet and date from 1939 to 1977. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including extensive correspondence from Sterne's second husband, the artist and New Yorker illustrator Saul Steinberg; writings; exhibition files; printed material; drawings and 3 sketchbooks; photographs and slides of Sterne, her family, and her work; and originals of Antoine de Saint-Exupéry's work Lettre A Leon Werth and 4 drawings Saint-Exupéry sent to Sterne.
Biographical material includes certificates, curriculum vitae, a Fulbright application, lists of artworks, and Saul Steinberg's fingerprints. Correspondence is primarily with Sterne's friends, and business associates. There is significant correspondence from the artist Georges Mathieu and from her second husband Saul Steinberg.
Writings consist of numerous miscellaneous handwritten and typescript notes on art. Exhibition files include an article, interview transcript, and press release for Sterne's 1970 exhibition "Everyone" at the Betty Parsons Gallery.Printed material includes cards, clippings, exhibition announcements and an exhibition catalog.
Artwork consists of drawings and 3 sketchbooks.
Photographs are of Sterne, her family and friends, and her artwork.
Materials related to Antoine de Saint-Exupéry include copies of his Lettre A Leon Werth and 4 drawings Saint-Exupéry sent to Sterne.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical materials, 1941-1970 (8 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1943-1965 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1945-1965 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Exhibitions, 1970 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed material, 1946-1977 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1945-1965 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 7: Photographs, 1939-1969 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 8: Antoine de Saint Exupéry, circa 1942 (4 folders; Box 1)
Betty Parsons Gallery.; Mathieu, Georges, 1921 -- Photographs; Saint-Exupéry, Antoine de, 1900-1944; Steinberg, Saul; Werth, Léon, 1878-1955; Drawings; Interviews; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, Modern--20th century--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Transcripts; Women painters--New York (State)--New York
- Biographical Materials, 1941-1970; Series 1; 8 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists of certificates and identification, curriculum vitae, contracts and forms, a Fulbright application, lists of artworks from 1952-1954, and Saul Steinberg's fingerprints.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Certificates, 1941-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Customs Forms, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Employment Contract, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fulbright Application, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Identification Card, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - List of Artworks, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Saul Steinberg Fingerprints, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, circa 1943-1965; Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Correspondence is primarily with Sterne's friends, and business associates, including limited correspondence with Ad Reinhardt and Eugene Berman. The series also includes significant correspondence from the artist Georges Mathieu and from her second husband, the artist and New Yorker illustrator Saul Steinberg. The letters from Steinberg date from his service in the Navy in 1943 to 1962, and include love letters, illustrated letters, notes, drawings, and descriptions of his work and daily life while traveling abroad or separately from Sterne.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A-Z Miscellaneous, circa 1949-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mathieu, Georges, circa 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Oversized correspondence housed in Box 2, Folder 1.
  - Steinberg, Saul, circa 1943-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes two letters to Saul Steinberg from Gump's Gallery (1952) and Bill Whitney (circa 1943-1963).
  - Steinberg, Saul (drawings), circa 1943-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20-24)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Illegible and Unknown, circa 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Oversized Correspondence from Box 1, Folder 10, circa 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Writings, circa 1945-1965; Series 3; 5 Folders Box 1
  Writings consist of numerous miscellaneous handwritten and typescript notes on art with references to art theory, literature, philosophy, biology, and psychiatry.
  - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 30-32)
  - Miscellaneous Notes (collated), circa 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
- Exhibitions, 1970; Series 4; 3 Folders Box 1
  Exhibition files includes an article by Walter Abish, an interview transcript, and a press release for Sterne's 1970 exhibition "Everyone" at the Betty Parsons Gallery.
  - Betty Parsons Gallery - "Everyone" (1970), Article by Walter Abish (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Betty Parsons Gallery - "Everyone" (1970), Interview Transcript (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Betty Parsons Gallery - "Everyone" (1970), Press Release (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Printed Material, 1946-1977; Series 5; 3 Folders Box 1
  Printed material includes cards, clippings, exhibition announcements and an exhibition catalog for Sterne's 1977 retrospective exhibition at the Montclair Art Museum.
  - Cards, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Clippings, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1946-1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Artwork, circa 1945-1965; Series 6; 2 Folders Box 1
  Artwork consists of drawings and 3 sketchbooks with a few abstract ink sketches.
  - Drawings, circa 1953 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Photographs, 1939-1969; Series 7; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Photographs are of Sterne, Sterne with Saul Steinberg and others, and of artwork. Two of the photographs of Sterne and Steinberg were taken by fashion photographers Irving Penn and George Platt Lynes respectively, two photos of Hedda Sterne was taken by Evelyn Hofer, and a color photo taken by Margaret Bourke White.
  Materials are arranged by document type and subject matter.
  - Photographs of Hedda Sterne, circa 1947-1969 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Oversized photograph housed in Box 2, Folder 2.
  - Photographs of Hedda Sterne and Saul Steinberg, 1944-1969 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Oversized photographs housed in Box 2, Folder 3.
  - Photographs of Artwork, Early Paintings, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1950s, Abstract Paintings, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1950s, Figurative Paintings, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1960s, Faces, circa 1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Oversized photograph housed in Box 2, Folder 4
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1960s, Ink Washes, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1960s, Lines, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Photographs of Artwork, 1960s, Pen and Ink, circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Sculptures, 1937-1949 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Oversized photograph from Box 1, Folder 43, circa 1947-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Oversized photographs from Box 1, Folder 44, circa 1944-1950 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Oversized photograph from Box 1, Folder 48, circa 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Antoine de Saint Exupéry, circa 1942; Series 8; 4 Folders Box 1
  Materials include a manuscript, typescript, and gallery proof of Saint-Exupéry's Lettre A Leon Werth, Saint-Exupéry's introduction to his friend Leon Werth's memoir 33 Jours. The manuscript has been revised and hand corrected by Saint-Exupéry throughout, and the gallery proof includes a brief inscription by Saint-Exupéry to Sterne. This series also includes 4 pen and ink drawings of "Little Prince" like characters Saint-Exupéry sent to Sterne.
  - Writings, Lettre A Leon Werth (manuscript), circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Writings, Lettre A Leon Werth (typescript), circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Writings, Lettre A Leon Werth (gallery proof), circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Artwork, Drawings, circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 57)